This is the most determined man I've ever met.
The Great Omani.
Inspired by Houdini, he spent a lifetime performing dangerous stunts.
And even in the last days of his life, he was still planning his next performance.
I'm still the oldest stuntman in the world.
The first time I met the Great Omani, he was being filmed by a South Korean television crew.
All I knew about him then was what I had read from local papers as I was growing up in Brighton.
That his real name was Ron Cunningham and as a young man, he'd run away from his wealthy family and joined the circus.
A bit more longer please.
Yeah, I tell you when.
So, Ron, um, how is your condition now?
Well, not too good this morning.
Earlier...
I had a very bad night.
Yesterday, as you may remember, we did about six hours filming and a lot of work went into that and I...
Sorry, sorry, I'm sorry.
Cut, cut, cut.
Because, um, sorry, you know, nobody wants to know that we spent six hours filming.
If we could stick with the story, OK?
No you can say you were nervous, excited, um yeah?
No sleep, OK?
But, um you don't have to say...
No, I'm sure.
Sorry.
Viewers don't need to know that, I know that.
All right, OK, OK.
After the warm up, Ron took the Koreans to the pub next to his house where he wanted to show them what the Great Omani could do.
Ladies and gentlemen, the world is full of very weird things and we have one of them here this evening.
This is the Great Omani.
You know, but don't worry about...
The Great Omaaa-neeee...
Sorry.
OK.
The world is full of weird and wonderful things.
I like to introduce you to one of the most bizarre people I've ever met, the Great Omani.
Oh, my God.
Hey, hup!
Oh, he's OK.
Oh, I can't believe.
I'm going to place the milk bottle on my throat, and smash the bottle with the hammer.
One.
Two.
Three.
Oh!
I'd arranged to meet Ron at his home but then I had an unexpected call from him.
He'd suddenly been taken to hospital and wanted me to come and see him there.
Is Ron Cunningham here?
Yeah.
Whereabouts is he?
Ah, he's in bed four.
OK.
Thank you.
Ron.
Oh!
Sorry.
It's Daniel.
Oh, nice to see you.
Sorry to give you a shock.
Were you sleeping?
All I have to do is sit here and dream.
Very nice.
But, um, yeah, a camera.
It's always rolling.
Want sunglasses on or off?
It's up to you.
They're a bit wonky, aren't they?
Unfortunately, last time we met I was pretty strong and well but I've recently suffered a stroke on the left side which means my left arm is... hardly any strength in it at all.
But I think with treatment at this hospital, they will get me well.
You see I've still got a good right hand, which is useful for smashing a bottle on the throat and also for picking up the odd pint of beer.
That's most important, to keep the right hand going.
Actually, at the moment, at this moment of talking, I'm officially the oldest stuntman in the world.
Ron made a quick recovery and was out of the hospital within a week.
The stroke had left him with only partial use of his legs and now he needed full-time help.
But Ron did not want to go into a home so he'd persuaded his son David to be his full-time carer.
And although David had agreed, it was on one condition - that Ron would finally give up performing dangerous stunts.
Are you OK, David?
Yeah, of course I'm all right.
It's not all that far now.
Nice coffee?
Lovely coffee, lovely.
Are you warm enough?
I'm sweating like a pig.
Right, one with me, up.
Same again.
One, two, three, push.
I've got you.
Ron and David had lived together since Ron's wife and stage assistant Eileen died 20 years ago.
David had reluctantly stepped into the world of show business and taken over his mother's job.
I'm on camera so...
Well, now, I'm...
I'm hoping to do my last final stunt.
Now I say I'm hoping because...
David is absolutely against it.
Is that true, David?
That's perfectly true.
Where stunts are concerned, especially now, I'm completely finished.
I never did like show business, personally.
He knows that as well as me.
I love show business and he's totally against it.
What are your objections?
Well, I mean, I just don't want him to do any more.
The brain's willing but the body has gone.
Simple as that.
It's ah, he's a cabbage with a brain still working but the body's not.
But this one... if I can get David to see my point of view, which I don't think he will...
Um, I don't want to go against him because he's been so good to me, but there's one big stunt I want to do, one final one, which will be a goodbye stunt, to the newspapers, the people who have been so kind to me, to my public.
In fact I could say worldwide because some of my stunts have been filmed worldwide.
But I have got one really good farewell one.
I think you'll find David's a very hard, tough man.
David, one moment, please.
David is a very tough, very strong, hard man, as you probably may know, but he's also got a heart of gold, heart of gold, and I think you'll find he'll give in, in the end.
I hope.
Anyway, Dave, here's to you and all you've done for me.
The next time I saw Ron, he was on his way to hospital for his regular dialysis treatment.
His kidneys were failing and he also told me that he'd been diagnosed with prostate cancer.
Despite this, I knew that Ron's main worry was not his failing health but David's objections to helping him perform another stunt.
What makes him think in that way?
I mean, especially, I would have thought, he'd have been quite proud of it and love it.
I mean I've broken quite a number of records and other things and you'd think... as his father, he'd be proud of it but...
I, I, I just...
I just do not know the answer to that question, why he hates it.
All I can tell you, he definitely does.
This is another stunt we've got lined up.
Um, this is a combination of escapology and fire.
You don't very often see this.
As you see, I'm being securely bound.
Now in a moment there will be a hood placed over my head.
Not just yet I think Dave, otherwise they won't be able to listen to me, nor see me, which is even worse.
It's all in a day's work for me.
But the point is, thing is, one day something is going to happen which he is going to come unstuck.
Well, that's his view.
It's in my view, it's been in my mind, been in my mind for donkey's years.
Why do you do it, if you're worried he's going to get hurt?
Well, at least I know what I'm doing.
And someone else...
Might make a mistake, yes.
Not only make a mistake.
With your own father you're just... a little bit more cautious of what you do.
Try and keep your feet down.
That's it.
Right.
There you are, gentlemen.
I hope you enjoyed it, and, er...
I would think probably, in a few months' time I will have another, shall we say, unusual escape for you.
Do you feel better now?
Yes, dear, thank you.
OK.
I said he won't be doing many stunts today.
It wasn't long before I had a call from Ron.
He'd convinced David to help him perform another stunt by promising that this would be the Great Omani's last-ever show.
Hello?
Who is it?
David, Ron.
What?
It's Daniel.
Oh, it's Daniel.
Come in Daniel.
Come in.
Ah, lovely to see you again.
Well, I'm actually upside down and you can understand...
I had no idea what Ron had planned but I wasn't sure he'd be able to do very much in his condition.
My wrists will be chained and padlocked to a steel bar, ah, padlocked, well padlocked up.
Then, my coat will be covered with cotton wool which will be petrol-soaked.
Then there'll be a chain around the outside of my arms.
So, all in all, a pretty tough proposition to get out of.
Now, my assistant will light the petrol and zoom, up it will go.
To see a man blazing up on fire, with his arms on fire, his hands chained, padlocked and handcuffed, well, you won't see that very often anywhere.
In fact, I don't think you'll see it anywhere at all.
I'm a little bit worried about it, I must say.
You're a little bit worried about it?
Well, I must say I am too but... no, I think I've got it pretty well worked out.
We're going the main one.
Ron had arranged for some journalists to turn up, billing it as the last ever performance of the world's oldest stuntman.
Hello, hello.
Right, ready?
Nearly.
What do we put on first?
The coat?
Well, of course.
OK.
Ah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Right.
The hat.
Then the arms, and then we've only got a few seconds to make my escape in this.
David, put the fire out.
My feet, David.
Ow!
Other side, come on!
Take your coat off.
Ladies and gentlemen.
Thank you very much.
You're not going to do it any more.
It proves one thing.
I'm getting a bit too old for these stunts.
It got a bit out of control which proves, you see, I've now got to the age, by gosh, I got to this age years ago, where I was thinking about retiring.
I was just a bit on the slow side, I definitely got a couple of burns, um, but all in all, I think it went pretty well.
I had no idea what was driving Ron to take such risks.
It seemed to be something that went a lot deeper than just entertaining and getting his name in the paper.
I wanted to know why he'd chosen this way of life.
Ron was not born into a world of show business.
His father, a successful wine importer, had hoped his son would take over the family company.
But Ron had other ideas.
When his father died, the business collapsed, their manor house was sold and the family fortunes lost.
Let me tell you something... the Great Omani.
You've got some match on your lip.
Yeah, you're right now.
I'll get you an ashtray, Ron.
When I was a child, when I was born, I was born, luckily, to a very wealthy family.
I tell you this because I was a very, very backward child.
Bottom of every class in every school.
Backward?
I'm surprised.
Very, very backward child.
Couldn't read or write for ages.
So that makes you wonder why from the most backward boy in any school which would have me, I became the Great Omani.
Did you have something to prove?
A boy did more than any of them.
You've always wanted to be...
Yes.
Yes, I've always wanted to leave my mark.
Why?
For my family's sake as well.
Why did you want to leave your mark?
Well, isn't is rather nice to, to have been someone?
If I leave my mark, it means I've been someone and I think that's rather nice.
Did you want to prove yourself not just to yourself but to your parents as well?
They would have been very proud, wouldn't they, of what you've done?
My mother would have been.
Yes, I think they would.
Beautiful stuff, it's strong.
So who would you be without the Great Omani?
Who would I be without the Great Omani?
A useless waste of...
I am still the oldest stuntman in the world.
This is the restraint that the great Houdini once said is one of the hardest restraints in the world to get out of.
And he knew what he was talking about.
Right, now this boy really knows how to put the straitjacket on.
There you are, that's what not to do with your broken bottles.
Well, Great Omani, you seem to have damaged your stomach a little.
The stunt is dangerous.
Obviously any stunts with fire or glass are dangerous.
That's why I said earlier, I don't know whether you caught this on camera, but I'd like to say I do hope nobody will try to reproduce these stunts in any way because they are, obviously, highly dangerous.
Give him a kiss.
Oh.
Good girl.
Oh, good.
OK, was that all right?
Can I ask you how it's been recently, looking after your dad?
He seems to be improving.
Yeah?
Oh, good.
To me he seems a bit easier but trouble is, he's still planning stunts, which does my brain in.
I can't, I can sit in the kitchen trying to watch television, "I've got a stunt, I might be able to do a stunt," and so I've got to shut the kitchen door.
But just one thing, Dave, if I can do one last stunt, David.
Yeah, but what can you do?
You can't even hold a glass, Dad.
The only thing you can do is maybe stick a torch up your backside, alight.
Burn your prostate out.
Cos in the old days...
All right, David.
Burn it out.
All right.
I've got to, I've got to get one going somewhere.
Otherwise people will be saying - who is the Great Omani?
I don't want it to get to that stage.
Over the next few weeks, Ron's health deteriorated.
Even so, he would not give up on the idea of performing again as the Great Omani.
The last stunt has got to be the big one.
Nothing less.
Ron needed looking after 24 hours a day and still didn't want to go into a care home.
This was putting a lot of strain on David.
So you wouldn't, you'd say no to Ron doing one little...
Yeah, yeah, I would, yeah.
I've had enough, honestly.
He could do it if he went in a home, it would be a pleasure.
David.
I'll cut your cigars out if you keep on.
Bring me a cigar, Dave.
Come on, open.
Mmm.
You give me a call when you've had it, I'll put it out, OK?
What have you done?
Got it.
Have you?
No more.
That was stupid.
I'm going to sit down now and have a cup of tea.
You have a rest.
You may be the oldest stuntman in Britain, Dad, but I'm the oldest slave in Britain.
Ha ha.
I like that.
I tell you what might be nice, Dave is...
Oh, what now, Dad!?
Oh.
Sorry, sorry.
It must be a difficult time right now for him.
Yeah and what about myself just sitting here seeing him crack up, see?
Quicker he goes, the better.
I'm not being cruel.
So I can, otherwise people say I'll end up dying.
Can't have that, can we Jessie?
Within a fortnight, Ron had made another miraculous recovery and told me he was going to perform a stunt on Easter Sunday.
Hello.
Come in, lad.
Come in.
Hello, Daniel.
Ron.
Hello.
You on the zimmer already?
Yeah, I've just...
I get very lazy otherwise.
Got the old camera and the sound...
You're looking very smart.
Thank you, thank you.
Yeah, very dapper.
How's your health since I last saw you, Ron?
You seem remarkably on form, considering last time I saw you you were...
Yeah, well, good days, bad days.
But, um... sometimes I feel like... funny thing is when the camera's on I always feel happy.
But I have had some... well, you, you...
I've been an escapologist most of my life and a good one but this is one thing you can't escape from.
You can beat man but you can't beat God and, er...
I got the illnesses so you've got to join them or you've got to adjust, adjust I think is possibly the word.
Sometimes I'm fine and happy like I am today.
Sometimes I get fits of depression.
But all in all I'm very lucky, I think.
RRRR!
Once again, Ron had arranged a small media circus, promoting the event as the last ever performance of the Great Omani.
He had also found a way round David's objections by getting the Mayor of Brighton to be his stage assistant.
I remember this young man 50 years ago when he used to jump off the West Pier into the water there, all chained up.
Ready?
Everyone ready?
Steady?
We all ready?
Thank you Mr Mayor, thank you very much.
The weeks rolled by and I heard nothing from Ron.
But then I had a call from David.
Ron's health had taken another turn for the worse.
The cancer was spreading rapidly.
He was almost completely paralysed and didn't have much longer to live.
Hello, Daniel.
I'll put his dinner away.
Oh, that's all right.
Let him eat Dave, let him eat.
It's all right.
No, it's all right.
In the oven.
Hello, how are you doing?
Hello, Ron.
Ah, you've got a new puppy.
David had borrowed the puppy from a friend in the hope it would cheer Ron up.
That's it, my old guard.
Good boy.
He's got my comb.
Jack, come and help, Jack.
Jack.
Ah.
That was a sharp bite.
No, Jack...
He's biting me.
Jack, no more.
No.
Jack.
I think he can smell there's something wrong with him.
What?
Death.
Dogs can smell that.
Really?
Oh, didn't you know that?
Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Yeah oh, yeah.
Doesn't seem quite himself.
He isn't, he isn't.
Keeps breaking down crying all of the time now but... what do you expect?
Mmmm.
There's so little I understand in life.
I'm not quite sure what I'm doing...
I just find life a big mystery.
I mean, for example, healthy strong male like myself, why should I be lying in a bed like this hardly able to move?
That's a mystery why that should happen.
Well, you are 92.
You are 92.
Part of the reason.
Yeah, that's...
That's old.
That's ah, that's a reasonable answer.
And yet it came so suddenly.
Yes, I won't argue against that because I can't.
You miss the feeling... of confidence... and power.
It's just not there.
Why has it been taken away?
I could see that Ron had accepted that the Great Omani's powers were slipping away.
But Ron still had one trick up his sleeve, an idea that would revive the Great Omani one last time.
Right, now we plan our next stunt.
This is the Great Omani speaking.
Well, we, I think we've got quite a good story here.
Ron was planning his funeral and was calling all his contacts in the press to make sure the newspapers wouldn't forget to write his obituary.
This is Omani, the brightest stuntman, the Great Omani.
There could be a story here.
The name's Omani, it should be fairly well known to you.
I may have a bit of a story for you.
Yes, indeed, a very unusual story.
You have heard of me, haven't you?
Oh, yes, of course you have.
By the way...
No!
Jack.
Once Ron had finished making his calls, he had a meeting with his undertaker.
Please excuse us smoking.
Hello.
Hello, I'm Theresa, hello.
Pleased to meet you.
I'm very pleased to meet you, very honoured to meet you.
Let's get the doggie off that way OK.
I'm not used to meeting ladies in your line of profession, as you may understand.
But, um...
Are they all as pretty as you?
Oh, I don't think so.
Ron went through his plans.
He wanted white horses to pull his hearse through Brighton city centre and he'd written an epitaph to be read out at the end of the service.
I go under the name of, of course, the Great Omani.
So here's my little poem.
They put Omani in his box.
They're using nails instead of locks.
But at his funeral, don't despair, The chances are he won't be there.
Do you like that one?
Yes, yes, it's good.
Thank you.
With that I'll say goodbye.
Thank you and God bless you.
All right.
You take care of yourself.
Nice to meet you.
Lovely to meet you.
Thank you for coming, nice to meet you.
The Great Omani signing off... and thanking you very much indeed.
When I say the Great Omani I should say, what's left of him.
We still salute you.
Thank you and BBC, thank you very much for coming along.
A few days later, Ron passed away after a cigar and a glass of whisky.
And as he had planned, his death did not go unnoticed.
I found his obituary featured in The Times, The Telegraph, The Independent, and dozens of papers in Britain and across the world, from the New Zealand Herald to the Illinois Journal.
He's at peace.
Looks a lot younger and all.
Actually, he never looked old anyhow for a 92, did he?
Has it been strange since he's gone?
The house is weird, I hear his voice but, then again, it's in my head at the moment.
What do you hear him saying?
Usual routine, five in the morning, "David, a cup of tea," or "David, my bag's full up."
Or if he's in a bad mood, "David, you lazy bastard."
You're peaceful now, Dad, aren't you, eh?
You'll be up with Houdini, all the doggies.
God rest you, Dad.
I'm...
I'm afraid I have to go now.
Upsetting me a bit, which is understandable.
He's at peace.